<!--
  ~ Copyright 2009 the original author or authors.
  ~
  ~ Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  ~ you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  ~ You may obtain a copy of the License at
  ~
  ~      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  ~
  ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  ~ distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  ~ WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  ~ See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  ~ limitations under the License.
  -->
<chapter id="working_with_files" xml:lang="ja">
    <title>ファイルを取り扱う <phrase role="original">Working With Files</phrase></title>
    <para role="original">
        Most builds work with files. Gradle adds some concepts and APIs to help you achieve this.
    </para>
    <para>
        ファイルの取り扱いは、ほとんどのビルドで発生する作業です。なので、それを補助するため、Gradleはいくつかの概念とAPIを導入しています。
    </para>

    <section id="sec:locating_files">
        <title>ファイルを参照する <phrase role="original">Locating files</phrase></title>
        <para role="original">You can locate a file relative to the project directory using the
            <apilink class="org.gradle.api.Project" method="file(java.lang.Object)"/> method.
        </para>
        <para><apilink class="org.gradle.api.Project" method="file(java.lang.Object)"/> メソッドで、プロジェクトディレクトリからの相対参照でファイルを取得できます。
        </para>
        <sample id="resolveFile" dir="userguide/files/file" title="ファイルを参照する / Locating files">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle"/>
        </sample>
        <para role="original">You can pass any object to the <literal>file()</literal> method, and it will attempt to convert the value
            to an absolute <classname>File</classname> object. Usually, you would pass it a
            <classname>String</classname> or <classname>File</classname> instance. The supplied object's
            <literal>toString()</literal> value is used as the file path. If this path is an absolute path, it is used
            to construct a <classname>File</classname> instance. Otherwise, a <classname>File</classname> instance is
            constructed by prepending the project directory path to the supplied path. The <literal>file()</literal>
            method also understands URLs, such as <literal>file:/some/path.xml</literal>.
        </para>
        <para><literal>file()</literal>メソッドには、あらゆるオブジェクトを渡すことができます。渡したオブジェクトは、絶対参照の<classname>File</classname>に変換されます。大抵は<classname>String</classname>か<classname>File</classname>のインスタンスを渡すことになるでしょう。渡されたオブジェクトの<literal>toString()</literal>が呼ばれ、その返値がファイルパスとして使われます。もしそのパスが絶対パスだった場合、そのパスで<classname>File</classname>インスタンスが構築されます。そうでなければ、プロジェクトディレクリのパスを先頭に追加してから<classname>File</classname>インスタンスが構築されます。また、<literal>file()</literal>メソッドは<literal>file:/some/path.xml</literal>のようなURLにも対応しています。
        </para>
        <para role="original">Using this method is a useful way to convert some user provided value into an absolute <classname>File</classname>.
            It is preferable to using <literal>new File(somePath)</literal>, as <literal>file()</literal> always evaluates
            the supplied path relative to the project directory, which is fixed, rather than the current working
            directory, which can change depending on how the user runs Gradle.
        </para>
        <para>
            このメソッドを使って、ユーザーが指定した値を簡単に絶対参照の<classname>File</classname>インスタンスに変換できます。
            これは、<classname>new File(somePath)</classname>を使うよりもよい方法でしょう。<literal>file()</literal>メソッドは、常にプロジェクトディレクリからの相対参照で解決されるからです。ワーキングディレクトリはGradleをどう実行したかによって変化しうるわけですが、それに依存せずにファイルを参照できます。
        </para>
    </section>

    <section id="sec:file_collections">
        <title>ファイルコレクション <phrase role="original">File collections</phrase></title>

        <para role="original">
            A <firstterm>file collection</firstterm> is simply a set of files. It is represented by the
            <apilink class="org.gradle.api.file.FileCollection"/> interface. Many objects in the Gradle API implement
            this interface. For example, <link linkend="sub:configurations">dependency configurations</link> implement
            <literal>FileCollection</literal>.
        </para>
        <para>
        <firstterm>ファイルコレクション</firstterm>は、単なるファイルの集合です。これは、<apilink class="org.gradle.api.file.FileCollection"/>インターフェースで表現されます。Gradle APIに含まれる多くのオブジェクトがこのインターフェースを実装しています。例えば、<link linkend="sub:configurations">依存関係のコンフィグレーション</link>もこの<literal>FileCollection</literal>インターフェースを実装しています。
        </para>

        <para role="original">
            One way to obtain a <literal>FileCollection</literal> instance is to use the
            <apilink class="org.gradle.api.Project" method="files(java.lang.Object...)"/> method. You can pass this method any number of
            objects, which are then converted into a set of <classname>File</classname> objects. The
            <literal>files()</literal> method accepts any type of object as its parameters. These are evaluated relative
            to the project directory, as per the <literal>file()</literal> method, described in <xref linkend="sec:locating_files"/>.
            You can also pass collections, iterables, maps and arrays to the <literal>files()</literal> method. These are flattened
            and the contents converted to <classname>File</classname> instances.
        </para>
        <para>
            <literal>FileCollection</literal>を取得する方法の一つは、<apilink class="org.gradle.api.Project" method="files(java.lang.Object...)"/>メソッドを使うことです。このメソッドには任意の数のオブジェクトを渡すことができ、渡したオブジェクトは<classname>File</classname>オブジェクトの集合に変換されます。これらのオブジェクトは、<xref linkend="sec:locating_files"/>で述べた<literal>file()</literal>メソッドと同じように、プロジェクトディレクトリからの相対参照で解決されます。
            また、コレクション、イテレーブル、マップ、配列を渡すこともできます。これらは、フラット化されてから、各要素が<classname>File</classname>インスタンスに変換されます。
        </para>

        <sample id="fileCollections" dir="userguide/files/fileCollections" title="ファイルコレクションの作成 / Creating a file collection">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="simple-params"/>
        </sample>

        <para role="original">A file collection is iterable, and can be converted to a number of other types using the <literal>as</literal>
            operator. You can also add 2 file collections together using the <literal>+</literal> operator, or subtract one
            file collection from another using the <literal>-</literal> operator.
            Here are some examples of what you can do with a file collection.
        </para>
        <para>
            ファイルコレクションはイテレーブルです。さらに、<literal>as</literal>演算子で様々な型に変換することができます。
            また、二つのファイルコレクションを<literal>+</literal>演算子で合成したり、<literal>-</literal>演算子でファイルコレクションから別のファイルコレクションの要素を取り除いたりすることができます。
            次の例は、ファイルコレクションでどのようなことができるかを示すものです。
        </para>
        <sample id="fileCollections" dir="userguide/files/fileCollections" title="ファイルコレクションを使う / Using a file collection">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="usage"/>
            <test args="-q usage"/>
        </sample>

        <para role="original">You can also pass the <literal>files()</literal> method a closure or a <classname>Callable</classname>
            instance. This is called when the contents of the collection are queried, and its return value is converted
            to a set of <classname>File</classname> instances. The return value can be an object of any of the types
            supported by the <literal>files()</literal> method. This is a simple way to 'implement' the
            <classname>FileCollection</classname> interface.
        </para>
        <para><literal>files()</literal>メソッドには、クロージャや<classname>Callable</classname>のインスタンスを渡すこともできます。
            これはそのファイルコレクションの内容が要求されたときに実行され、返値が<classname>File</classname>インスタンスの集合に変換されます。返値は<literal>files()</literal>に渡すことができるオブジェクトならなんでも構いません。これは、<classname>FileCollection</classname>インタフェースを簡単に「実装する」方法とも言えます。
        </para>
        <sample id="fileCollections" dir="userguide/files/fileCollections" title="ファイルコレクションを実装する / Implementing a file collection">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="closure"/>
            <output args="-q list"/>
        </sample>

        <para role="original">
            Some other types of things you can pass to <literal>files()</literal>:
        </para>
        <para>
            他にもいくつか<literal>files()</literal>メソッドに渡せる型があります。
        </para>
        <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><classname>FileCollection</classname></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para role="original">These are flattened and the contents included in the file collection.</para>
                    <para>フラット化されてから、その内容がファイルコレクションに追加される。</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><classname>Task</classname></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para role="original">The output files of the task are included in the file collection.</para>
                    <para>タスクの出力ファイルがファイルコレクションに追加される。</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><classname>TaskOutputs</classname></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para role="original">The output files of the TaskOutputs are included in the file collection.</para>
                    <para>TaskOutputsの出力ファイルがファイルコレクションに追加される。</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

        <para role="original">It is important to note that the content of a file collection is evaluated lazily, when it is needed.
            This means you can, for example, create a <literal>FileCollection</literal> that represents files which
            will be created in the future by, say, some task.
        </para>
        <para>留意すべき重要な点は、ファイルコレクションの内容は、必要になったときに遅延評価されるということです。
        これはつまり、例えば未来にタスクなどによって作られるであろうファイル群を表す<literal>FileCollection</literal>を作ることもできる、ということを意味します。
        </para>

    </section>

    <section id="sec:file_trees">
        <title>ファイルツリー <phrase role="original">File trees</phrase></title>

        <para role="original">
            A <firstterm>file tree</firstterm> is a collection of files arranged in a hierarchy. For example, a file tree
            might represent a directory tree or the contents of a ZIP file. It is represented
            by the <apilink class="org.gradle.api.file.FileTree"/> interface. The <literal>FileTree</literal> interface
            extends <literal>FileCollection</literal>, so you can treat a file tree exactly the same way as you would a
            file collection. Several objects in Gradle implement the <literal>FileTree</literal> interface, such as
            <link linkend="sec:source_sets">source sets</link>.
        </para>
        <para>
            ファイルツリーは、階層構造を持つファイルの集合です。例えば、ディレクトリツリーやZIPの中身を表すことができます。ファイルツリーは<apilink class="org.gradle.api.file.FileTree"/>インターフェースによって表現されます。<literal>FileTree</literal>インターフェースは<literal>FileCollection</literal>インターフェースを継承しています。なので、FileTreeはFileCollectionと全く同じ方法で取り扱うことができます。
            いくつかのGradleオブジェクトは<literal>FileTree</literal>を実装しています。例えば、<link linkend="sec:source_sets">ソースセット</link>などです。
        </para>

        <para role="original">
            One way to obtain a <literal>FileTree</literal> instance is to use the
            <apilink class="org.gradle.api.Project" method="fileTree(java.util.Map)"/> method.
            This creates a <literal>FileTree</literal> defined with a base directory, and optionally some Ant-style
            include and exclude patterns.
        </para>
        <para>
            <literal>FileTree</literal>インスタンスを取得する方法の一つは、<apilink class="org.gradle.api.Project" method="fileTree(java.util.Map)"/>メソッドを使用することです。
            このメソッドは、ベースディレクトリとAntスタイルのinclude/excludeパターンを指定して<literal>FileTree</literal>を構築します。
        </para>

        <sample id="fileTrees" dir="userguide/files/fileTrees" title="ファイルツリーを作成する / Creating a file tree">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="define"/>
        </sample>

        <para role="original">You use a file tree in the same way you use a file collection. You can also visit the contents of the
            tree, and select a sub-tree using Ant-style patterns:
        </para>
        <para>ファイルツリーは、ファイルコレクションと同じ方法で使うことができます。さらに、ツリー構造を辿ったり、Antスタイルのパターンを指定してサブツリーを選択することも可能です。</para>
        <sample id="fileTrees" dir="userguide/files/fileTrees" title="ファイルツリーを使う / Using a file tree">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="use"/>
        </sample>
    </section>

    <section id="sec:archive_contents">
        <title>アーカイブの内容をファイルツリーとして使う <phrase role="original">Using the contents of an archive as a file tree</phrase></title>

        <para role="original">You can use the contents of an archive, such as a ZIP or TAR file, as a file tree. You do this using
            the <apilink class="org.gradle.api.Project" method="zipTree"/> and
            <apilink class="org.gradle.api.Project" method="tarTree(java.lang.Object)"/> methods. These methods return a <literal>FileTree</literal>
            instance which you can use like any other file tree or file collection. For example, you can use it to expand
            the archive by copying the contents, or to merge some archives into another.
        </para>
        <para>ZIPやTARファイルなどのアーカイブを、ファイルツリーとして使うことができます。そのためのメソッドが、<apilink class="org.gradle.api.Project" method="zipTree"/>や<apilink class="org.gradle.api.Project" method="tarTree(java.lang.Object)"/>です。これらのメソッドは、<literal>FileTree</literal>インスタンスを返すもので、返されたインスタンスは、他のファイルツリーやファイルコレクションと同様に扱うことができます。
            例えば、内容をコピーすることでアーカイブを解凍したり、別のアーカイブとマージしたりできます。
        </para>
        <sample id="fileTrees" dir="userguide/files/fileTrees" title="アーカイブをファイルツリーとして使う / Using an archive as a file tree">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="archive-trees"/>
        </sample>
    </section>

    <section id="sec:specifying_multiple_files">
        <title>入力ファイルセットを指定する <phrase role="original">Specifying a set of input files</phrase></title>
        <para role="original">Many objects in Gradle have properties which accept a set of input files. For example, the
            <apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.compile.JavaCompile"/> task has a <literal>source</literal> property,
            which defines the source files to compile. You can set the value of this property using any of the types
            supported by the <link linkend="sec:file_collections">files()</link> method, which was shown above.
            This means you can set the property using, for example, a <classname>File</classname>, <classname>String</classname>,
            collection, <classname>FileCollection</classname> or even a closure.
            Here are some examples:
        </para>
        <para>多くのGradleオブジェクトが入力ファイルセットを格納できるプロパティを持っています。例えば、<apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.compile.JavaCompile"/>タスクには<literal>source</literal>プロパティがあり、コンパイルするべきソースファイルの集合をそこに定義します。
            このプロパティの値には、<literal>files()</literal>でサポートされている、上記の全ての型が使用可能です。
            つまり、<classname>File</classname>、<literal>String</literal>、コレクション、<classname>FileCollection</classname>、クロージャでさえセット可能ということです。次の例を見てください。
        </para>
        <sample id="inputFiles" dir="userguide/files/inputFiles" title="ファイルセットを指定する / Specifying a set of files">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="set-input-files"/>
        </sample>
        <para role="original">Usually, there is a method with the same name as the property, which appends to the set of files. Again,
            this method accepts any of the types supported by the <link linkend="sec:file_collections">files()</link>
            method.
        </para>
        <para>大抵、そのプロパティと同名のメソッドも定義されていて、そのメソッドでファイルセットを追加できるようになっています。このメソッドにも<link linkend="sec:file_collections">files()</link>でサポートされている全ての型を渡すことができます。
        </para>
        <sample id="inputFiles" dir="userguide/files/inputFiles" title="ファイルセットを指定する / Specifying a set of files">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="add-input-files"/>
        </sample>
    </section>

    <section id="sec:copying_files">
        <title>ファイルをコピーする <phrase role="original">Copying files</phrase></title>
        <para role="original">You can use the <apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.Copy"/> task to copy files. The copy task is very flexible, and allows
            you to, for example, filter the contents of the files as they are copied, and map to the file names.
        </para>
        <para><apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.Copy"/>タスクを使ってファイルをコピーできます。このタスクはとても柔軟で、コピーしたファイルの内容をフィルターにかけたり、ファイル名をマッピングで変換したりできます。</para>
        <para role="original">To use the <literal>Copy</literal> task, you must provide a set of source files to copy, and a destination directory to copy
            the files to. You may also specify how to transform the files as they are copied. You do all this using a
            <firstterm>copy spec</firstterm>. A copy spec is represented by the <apilink class="org.gradle.api.file.CopySpec"/> interface. The
            <literal>Copy</literal> task implements this interface.
            You specify the source files using the <apilink class="org.gradle.api.file.CopySpec" method="from(java.lang.Object...)"/>
            method. To specify the destination directory, use the <apilink class="org.gradle.api.file.CopySpec" method="into(java.lang.Object)"/>
            method.
        </para>
        <para><literal>Copy</literal>タスクを使うには、コピーすべきソースファイルと、コピー先のディレクトリを指定しなければなりません。また、コピー時にファイルを編集する場合は、それについても指定します。これらの指定は全て、<firstterm>Copy仕様</firstterm>を使って行います。Copy仕様は、<apilink class="org.gradle.api.file.CopySpec"/>インターフェースで表現されており、<literal>Copy</literal>タスクはこのインターフェースを実装したものです。ソースファイルの指定には、<apilink class="org.gradle.api.file.CopySpec" method="from(java.lang.Object...)"/>メソッドを使います。コピー先ディレクトリの指定には、<apilink class="org.gradle.api.file.CopySpec" method="into(java.lang.Object)"/>メソッドを使います。
        </para>
        <sample id="copy" dir="userguide/files/copy" title="Copyタスクでファイルをコピーする / Copying files using the copy task">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="copy-task"/>
            <test args="test"/>
        </sample>
        <para role="original">The <literal>from()</literal> method accepts any of the arguments that the
            <link linkend="sec:file_collections">files()</link> method does. When an argument resolves to a directory,
            everything under that directory (but not the directory itself) is recursively copied into the destination
            directory. When an argument resolves to a file, that file is copied into the destination directory.
            When an argument resolves to a non-existing file, that argument is ignored. When an argument resolves to 
            a task (or explicitly its output), the output of the task is used as the argument for the <literal>from()</literal>
            method and this task is automatically added as a dependency of the <literal>Copy</literal> task.            
            The <literal>into()</literal> accepts
            any of the arguments that the <link linkend="sec:locating_files">file()</link> method does. Here is another
            example:
        </para>
        <para><literal>from()</literal>メソッドが受け付ける型は、<literal>files()</literal>メソッドと同じです。ディレクトリパスに解決されるような引数を渡した場合、そのディレクトリ以下の全て（ただし、そのディレクトリ自身は除く）が再帰的にターゲットディレクトリにコピーされます。渡した引数がファイルパスに解決された場合は、そのファイルが目的のディレクトリにコピーされます。
            もし、引数に渡したパスにファイルがない場合、その引数は無視されます。
            引数にタスク（または明示的にそのoutput）を渡した場合、そのタスクのoutputが<literal>from()</literal>の引数として使用され、そのタスクは自動的にCopyタスクが依存しているタスクとして設定されます。
            <literal>into()</literal>メソッドは、<literal>file()</literal>と同じ型を引数に取ります。以下にもう一つ例を挙げます。
        </para>
        <sample id="copy" dir="userguide/files/copy" title="Copyタスクのコピー元と宛先を指定する / Specifying copy task source files and destination directory">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="copy-task-2"/>
        </sample>
        <para role="original">You can select the files to copy using Ant-style include or exclude patterns, or using a closure:</para>
        <para>Antスタイルのinclude/excludeパターンかクロージャを用いて、コピーするファイルを選択することができます。</para>
        <sample id="copy" dir="userguide/files/copy" title="コピーするファイルを選択する / Selecting the files to copy">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="copy-task-with-patterns"/>
        </sample>
        <para role="original">You can also use the <apilink class="org.gradle.api.Project" method="copy"/> method to copy files. It works the
            same way as the task with some major limitations though. First, the <literal>copy()</literal> method can not automatically handle the up-to-date
            check of the copied files.
        </para>
        <para>また、<apilink class="org.gradle.api.Project" method="copy"/>メソッドでファイルをコピーすることもできます。これはタスクの場合と大体同じように動作しますが、いくつかの大きな制限もあります。まず、<literal>copy()</literal>メソッドはコピーされるファイルに対し自動的にはup-to-dateチェックを行いません。</para>
        <sample id="copy" dir="userguide/files/copy" title="Copying files using the copy() method without up-to-date check">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="copy-method"/>
        </sample>
        <para role="original">Secondly, the <literal>copy()</literal> method can not automatically add a task as a dependency when used as an argument
            of <literal>from()</literal>. Actually, in this situation, if this task is not explicitly declared as a dependency of the
            task enclosing the use of the <literal>copy()</literal> method, the dependent task will not be executed and either an out of
            date file will be copied or no file will be copied. Here is a verbose example of <literal>copy()</literal>
            method with up-to-date check and task dependency manually added to be at par with the <literal>Copy()</literal> task :
        </para>
        <para>次に、<literal>copy()</literal>メソッドは、タスクが<literal>from()</literal>メソッドの引数に渡されても、そのタスクを自動的に依存タスクに追加することはありません。
            実際、この場合は、<literal>copy()</literal>メソッドを呼び出しているタスクが依存しているタスクとして明示的に宣言されなければ、依存先のタスクは実行されず、古いファイルがコピーされたり、ファイルがコピーされなかったりするかもしれません。以下に<literal>copy()</literal>メソッドをup-to-dateチェックおよび手動によるCopy()タスクへの依存性の追加とともに使用する例について、詳しく注釈した例を挙げます。
        </para>
        <sample id="copy" dir="userguide/files/copy" title="up-to-dateチェックとともにcopy()メソッドでファイルをコピーする / Copying files using the copy() method with up-to-date check">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="copy-method-with-dependency"/>
        </sample>
        <para role="original">The bottom line is that the <literal>Copy()</literal> task should be preferred over the <literal>copy()</literal> method most of the time.
        </para>
        <para>要するに、ほとんどの場合<literal>copy()</literal>メソッドより<literal>Copy()</literal>タスクを使う方が望ましいということです。</para>
        <section>
            <title>ファイルをリネームする <phrase role="original">Renaming files</phrase></title>
            <sample id="renameOnCopy" dir="userguide/files/copy" title="コピー時にファイルをリネームする / Renaming files as they are copied">
                <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="rename-files"/>
            </sample>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>ファイルをフィルタリングする <phrase role="original">Filtering files</phrase></title>
            <sample id="filterOnCopy" dir="userguide/files/copy" title="コピー時にファイルをフィルタリングする / Filtering files as they are copied">
                <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="filter-files"/>
            </sample>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title><classname>CopySpec</classname>クラスを使う <phrase role="original">Using the <classname>CopySpec</classname> class</phrase></title>
            <para role="original">Copy specs form a hierarchy. A copy spec inherits its destination path, include patterns, exclude patterns, copy actions,
                name mappings and filters.</para>
            <para>コピー仕様は階層構造を構成でき、宛先パス、include/excludeパターン、コピー動作、ファイル名のマッピング、フィルターを継承できます。</para>
            <sample id="nestedCopySpecs" dir="userguide/files/copy" title="入れ子構造のコピー仕様 / Nested copy specs">
                <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="nested-specs"/>
            </sample>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section id="sec:sync_task">
        <title><literal>Sync</literal>タスクを使う <phrase role="original">Using the <literal>Sync</literal> task</phrase></title>
        <para role="original">The <apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.Sync"/> task extends the <literal>Copy</literal> task. When it
            executes, it copies the source files into the destination directory, and then removes any files from the
            destination directory which it did not copy. This can be useful for doing things such as installing your
            application, creating an exploded copy of your archives, or maintaining a copy of the project's dependencies.
        </para>
        <para><apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.Sync"/>は<literal>Copy</literal>タスクを継承したタスクです。このタスクは、宛先ディレクトリにファイルをコピーし、その後、コピーしたファイル以外の全ファイルを宛先ディレクトリから削除します。これは、アプリケーションをインストールしたり、アーカイブを解凍したり、プロジェクトの依存関係のコピーをメンテナンスしたりするのに便利です。</para>
        <para role="original">Here is an example which maintains a copy of the project's runtime dependencies in the <filename>build/libs</filename>
            directory.</para>
        <para>次の例では、<filename>build/libs</filename>にある実行時依存関係のコピーをメンテナンスしています。</para>
        <sample id="syncDependencies" dir="userguide/files/sync" title="Syncタスクで依存関係をコピーする / Using the Sync task to copy dependencies">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="copy-dependencies"/>
            <test args="libs"/>
        </sample>
    </section>

    <section id="sec:archives">
        <title>アーカイブを作成する <phrase role="original">Creating archives</phrase></title>
        <para role="original">
            A project can have as many as JAR archives as you want. You can also add WAR, ZIP and TAR archives to your project.
            Archives are created using the various archive tasks:
            <apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.bundling.Zip"/>,
            <apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.bundling.Tar"/>,
            <apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.bundling.Jar"/>,
            <apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.bundling.War"/>, and
            <apilink class="org.gradle.plugins.ear.Ear"/>.
            They all work the same way, so let's look at how you create a ZIP file.
        </para>
        <para>
            一つのプロジェクトで、JARファイルを好きなだけ作成することができます。WAR、ZIP、TARなどのアーカイブをプロジェクトに加えることもできます。
            アーカイブは、
            <apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.bundling.Zip"/>、
            <apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.bundling.Tar"/>、
            <apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.bundling.Jar"/>、
            <apilink class="org.gradle.api.tasks.bundling.War"/>、
            <apilink class="org.gradle.plugins.ear.Ear"/>などのアーカイブタスクを使って作成します。
            これらは全て同じ使い方なので、ここではZIPファイルの作成方法を見てみましょう。
        </para>
        <sample id="createZip" dir="userguide/files/archives" title="ZIPアーカイブの作成 / Creating a ZIP archive">
            <sourcefile file="build.gradle" snippet="zip"/>
        </sample>
        <tip>
            <title>なぜJavaプラグインを使うのですか？ <phrase role="original">Why are you using the Java plugin?</phrase></title>
            <para role="original">The Java plugin adds a number of default values for the archive tasks. You can use the archive
                tasks without using the Java plugin, if you like. You will need to provide values for some additional
                properties.
            </para>
            <para>
            Javaプラグインは、アーカイブタスクに多くのデフォルト値を追加します。必要なら、Javaプラグインなしでアーカイブタスクを使うことも可能です。その場合、いくつかのプロパティを自分で定義する必要があるでしょう。
            </para>
        </tip>

        <para role="original">
            The archive tasks all work exactly the same way as the <literal>Copy</literal> task, and implement the same
            <classname>CopySpec</classname> interface. As with the <literal>Copy</literal> task, you specify the input
            files using the <literal>from()</literal> method, and can optionally specify where they end up in the
            archive using the <literal>into()</literal> method. You can filter the contents of file, rename files, and
            all the other things you can do with a copy spec.
        </para>
        <para>アーカイブタスクは、全て<literal>Copy</literal>タスクと全く同じように動作します。これらのタスクは、Copyタスク同様、<classname>CopySpec</classname>インターフェースを実装しています。<literal>Copy</literal>タスクと同じように<literal>from()</literal>メソッドで入力ファイルを指定し、必須ではありませんが<literal>into()</literal>メソッドで最終的にアーカイブが出力される場所を指定します。ファイルのフィルタリング、リネーム、その他コピー仕様で使える全てのオプションを使うことができます。</para>

        <section>
            <title>アーカイブのネーミング <phrase role="original">Archive naming</phrase></title>

            <para role="original">The default name for a generated archive is <filename><replaceable>projectName</replaceable>-<replaceable>version</replaceable>.<replaceable>type</replaceable></filename>
                For example:
            </para>
            <para>作成されるアーカイブの名前は、デフォルトでは<filename><replaceable>projectName</replaceable>-<replaceable>version</replaceable>.<replaceable>type</replaceable></filename>です。例えば、</para>
            <sample id="archiveNaming" dir="userguide/files/archiveNaming" title="ZIPアーカイブの作成 / Creation of ZIP archive">
                <sourcefile file="build.gradle"/>
                <output args="-q myZip"/>
            </sample>

            <para role="original">This adds a <classname>Zip</classname> archive task with the name <literal>myZip</literal> which produces
                ZIP file <filename>zipProject-1.0.zip</filename>. It is important to distinguish between the name of the archive task
                and the name of the archive generated by the archive task. The default name for archives can be
                changed with the <literal>archivesBaseName</literal> project property. The name of the archive can also be
                changed at any time later on.</para>
            <para>ここでは、myZipという名前の<classname>Zip</classname>アーカイブタスクが、<filename>zipProject-1.-.zip</filename>というZIPファイルを作成しています。大事なことは、アーカイブタスクの名前と、そのタスクで作成したアーカイブ名に関連がないことです。デフォルトのアーカイブ名は、プロジェクトの<literal>archivesBaseName</literal>プロパティで変更できます。そのアーカイブ名も、後からいつでも変更可能です。</para>

            <para role="original">There are a number of properties which you can set on an archive task. These are listed below in <xref linkend="archiveTasksNamingProperties"/>.
                You can, for example, change the name of the archive:
            </para>
            <para>アーカイブタスクにセットできるプロパティはたくさんあります。それらを下の<xref linkend="archiveTasksNamingProperties"/>にリストしました。例えば、アーカイブの名前を変更したい場合は次のようにします。</para>
            <sample id="zipWithCustomName" dir="userguide/tutorial/zipWithCustomName" title="アーカイブタスクの設定 - カスタムアーカイブ名 / Configuration of archive task - custom archive name">
                <sourcefile file="build.gradle"/>
                <output args="-q myZip"/>
            </sample>
            <para role="original">You can further customize the archive names:</para>
            <para>アーカイブ名をさらにカスタマイズすることもできます。</para>
            <sample id="zipWithArguments" dir="userguide/tutorial/zipWithArguments" title="アーカイブタスクの設定 - appendix &amp; classifier / Configuration of archive task - appendix &amp; classifier">
                <sourcefile file="build.gradle"/>
                <output args="-q myZip"/>
            </sample>

            <table id="archiveTasksNamingProperties">
                <title>アーカイブタスク - ネーミングプロパティ <phrase role="original">Archive tasks - naming properties</phrase></title>
                <thead>
                    <tr>
                        <td>プロパティ名 <phrase role="original">Property name</phrase></td>
                        <td>型 <phrase role="original">Type</phrase></td>
                        <td>デフォルト値 <phrase role="original">Default value</phrase></td>
                        <td>説明 <phrase role="original">Description</phrase></td>
                    </tr>
                </thead>
                <tr>
                    <td><literal>archiveName</literal></td>
                    <td><classname>String</classname></td>
                    <td>
                        <filename><replaceable>baseName</replaceable>-<replaceable>appendix</replaceable>-<replaceable>version</replaceable>-<replaceable>classifier</replaceable>.<replaceable>extension</replaceable></filename>
                        <para role="original">If any of these properties is empty the trailing <filename>-</filename> is not added to the name.</para>
                        <para>プロパティが空だった場合、それに伴う<filename>-</filename>も追加されない。</para>
                    </td>
                    <td>生成されるアーカイブのベースファイル名 <phrase role="original">The base file name of the generated archive</phrase></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td><literal>archivePath</literal></td>
                    <td><classname>File</classname></td>
                    <td><filename><replaceable>destinationDir</replaceable>/<replaceable>archiveName</replaceable></filename></td>
                    <td>生成されるアーカイブの絶対パス <phrase role="original">The absolute path of the generated archive.</phrase></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td><literal>destinationDir</literal></td>
                    <td><classname>File</classname></td>
                    <td>アーカイブの種類に依存する。JAR、WARの場合は<filename><replaceable>project.buildDir</replaceable>/libraries</filename>。ZIP、TARの場合は<filename><replaceable>project.buildDir</replaceable>/distributions</filename>。<phrase role="original">Depends on the archive type. JARs and WARs are generated into <filename><replaceable>project.buildDir</replaceable>/libraries</filename>.
                        ZIPs and TARs are generated into <filename><replaceable>project.buildDir</replaceable>/distributions</filename>.</phrase>
                    </td>
                    <td>アーカイブが生成されるディレクトリ <phrase role="original">The directory to generate the archive into</phrase></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td><literal>baseName</literal></td>
                    <td><classname>String</classname></td>
                    <td><filename><replaceable>project.name</replaceable></filename></td>
                    <td>アーカイブ名の「ベース名」部 <phrase role="original">The base name portion of the archive file name.</phrase></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td><literal>appendix</literal></td>
                    <td><classname>String</classname></td>
                    <td><literal>null</literal></td>
                    <td>アーカイブ名の「付加」部 <phrase role="original">The appendix portion of the archive file name.</phrase></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td><literal>version</literal></td>
                    <td><classname>String</classname></td>
                    <td><filename><replaceable>project.version</replaceable></filename></td>
                    <td>アーカイブ名の「バージョン」部 <phrase role="original">The version portion of the archive file name.</phrase></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td><literal>classifier</literal></td>
                    <td><classname>String</classname></td>
                    <td><literal>null</literal></td>
                    <td>アーカイブ名の「分類子」部 <phrase role="original">The classifier portion of the archive file name,</phrase></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td><literal>extension</literal></td>
                    <td><classname>String</classname></td>
                    <td>アーカイブの種類に依存する。TARファイルの場合、圧縮方法にも依存する。<phrase role="original">Depends on the archive type, and for TAR files, the compression type as well: </phrase><filename>zip</filename>, <filename>jar</filename>,
                        <filename>war</filename>, <filename>tar</filename>, <filename>tgz</filename> or <filename>tbz2</filename>.</td>
                    <td>アーカイブ名の拡張子 <phrase role="original">The extension of the archive file name.</phrase></td>
                </tr>
            </table>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>複数のアーカイブで中身を共有する <phrase role="original">Sharing content between multiple archives</phrase></title>
            <para role="original">You can use the <apilink class="org.gradle.api.Project" method="copySpec"/> method to share content between archives.</para>
            <para><apilink class="org.gradle.api.Project" method="copySpec"/>メソッドを使ってアーカイブ間で中身を共有できます。</para>
        </section>

        <para role="original">Often you will want to publish an archive, so that it is usable from another project. This process is
            described in <xref linkend="artifact_management"/>
        </para>
        <para>アーカイブを別のプロジェクトで使えるようにするために、そのアーカイブを公開したくなることがよくあります。この処理については、<xref linkend="artifact_management"/>に記載されています。</para>

    </section>

</chapter>
